in this video we're going to talk about
how to solve
problems associated with the physical
pendulum
so in this example we have a 1.5 meter
uniform rod
with a mass of 0.6 kilograms
and it's acting as a physical pendulum
as you can see in the figure below
what is the inertia of the rod about its
axis of rotation
so it rotates about this point
l
is the length of the rod
and to calculate the inertia of a rod
where the axis of rotation is at the end
of the rod
it's 1 3
m l
squared so that's 1 3 times the mass
which is 0.6 kilograms
and the length is 1.5 meters
so 1.5 squared times 0.6 divided by 3
that will give us an inertia of 0.45
kilograms times square meters
so that's the solution to part a
now let's move on to part b
what is the period of the pendulum
the period of the pendulum is 2 pi
times the square root
of the inertia divided by
the mass
times the gravitational acceleration
times d
now d
is the distance between the axis of
rotation
and the center of gravity
so this is d in this example
because we're dealing with a uniform rod
we assume that the mass is distributed
uniformly
among that rod so the center of gravity
simply has to be at the middle
so d
is half of l
so if l is 1.5 d is
1.5 divided by 2 or 0.75
so the period is going to be 2 pi
times the square root of the inertia
which is 0.45
divided by the mass
which is 0.6 so g is 9.8
and d that's l over 2
so that's 1.5 over 2 or 0.75 meters
and so if you type this in
you should get a period
of about two seconds
so that's how you can calculate the
period of a physical pendulum
if the pendulum consists of
a long rod with nothing attached to it
now how can we calculate the period of a
physical pendulum
if
the rod is attached to a block
so we have the length of the rod it's
1.2 meters it's once again a uniform rod
and the mass of the rod is 0.5 kilograms
what is the total inertia of the rod and
the block
so let's say that the mass of the rod is
capital m
and
the mass of the block let's use
lowercase m
we know that the inertia of the rod
with the axis of rotation at the end of
the rod
is going to be 1 3
capital m times l squared
now the inertia of the block
relative to
the center or the axis of rotation
we could treat that as a point mass so
it's just going to be
m r squared or
which is basically the same as ml
squared
so all we got to do now is plug in the
values
so it's one-third
times the mass of the rod which is 0.5
kilograms
times the length of the rod
and that's 1.2 meters
plus
and it should be a lowercase m i don't
know why i made that a capital m
so it's going to be plus the mass of the
block which is 2 kilograms
times
the radius which is the length of the
rod that's still 1.2 meters squared
so 1.2 squared times 0.5 divided by 3
plus 2 times 1.2 squared
that will give us a total inertia
of 3.12 kilograms
times square meters
now before we can calculate the period
of the pendulum
we need to locate the center of mass
because we have a block attached to the
rod
the center of mass is not going to be in
the middle of the rod anymore
so we need to find it
so how can we find it
so let's say that
let's draw the horizontal version of
this picture
and we can say this is position zero
and this is the two kilogram mass
which is 1.2 meters away from the axis
of rotation
and the mass of the rod which is 0.5
kilograms
the center of the mass just of the rod
itself not the whole system that's going
to be right in the middle 0.6 meters
but we need to find the center of mass
for the rod and the block which is going
to be somewhere between 0.6 and 1.2
now because the block
has more mass than the rod
we should expect that the center of mass
should be closer to 1.2
than 0.6
so it should be between 0.9 and 1.2
now to calculate the answer let's get
let's use the center of mass equation so
it's going to be
mass 1 times position 1 plus
mass 2 times position 2
divided by the total mass
so the first mass let's use the mass of
the rod that's 0.5 and it's located at
position 0.6
right at the center of the rod
the second mass is located at position
1.2
and the total mass 0.5 plus 2
that's 2.5 kilograms
so 0.5 times 0.6
plus 2 times 1.2
divided by 2.5
that gives us a position
of 1.08 meters
so that's the location of the center of
mass for this particular pendulum
so now that we have that
we could say that this value is d
we can now
calculate the period of this pendulum
so it's going to be 2 pi
times the square root of the inertia
divided by
mgd
now this mass represents the total mass
that's the mass of the rod
and the block
so it's going to be 2 pi
times the square root of the inertia
which is 3.12
divided by
the mass of the block which is 2
kilograms plus the mass of the rod
that's 0.5 so
we have a total mass of 2.5
and g
is 9.8
and d in this example is 1.08
so go ahead and type that in
so 3.12 divided by 2.5
divided by 9.8 and then divide that
result by 1.08
that's a small number that's like 0.1179
and then take the square root of that
result and then multiply it by 2 pi
and so you should get a period of 2.16
seconds
and so that's the answer for this
problem
now it turns out that you could derive
the formula for a simple pendulum
from a physical pendulum
the period of a physical pendulum is
2 pi times the square root of the
inertia divided by
mgd and the period
for a simple pendulum is 2 pi
times the square root of l over g
let's see if we could take this formula
and turn it into this
so for a simple pendulum
we have basically a massless string
which means it doesn't have any inertia
and so all of the mass is concentrated
at this point
and so the inertia of the whole pendulum
is basically the inertia of this mass
around
this axis of rotation
and so the inertia of a point mass
is m r squared
and r is basically the length
of
the rope
or the cord
so the inertia is ml squared
now the location of the center of mass
is basically at this mass because the
string has no mass
so d
is going to be the same as l in this
problem
so we're going to have
the total mass of the pendulum which is
m again because all the mass is here
times g
and d is l
so we could cancel m
and we can cancel
one of the l values
and so we get this equation
2 pi
with one l left over divided by g
and so that's how you can derive
the formula of a simple pendulum
from the formula of a physical pendulum
you